Welcome back to Apush in under three
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. So in our last unit, we've
established that by the '80s, citizens
of America have lost confidence in the
greater American government for a
variety of reasons. So now, coming back
into this, people start to think maybe
the government is the problem, not the
solution. And that right there is the
opening for conservatives. Enter Ronald
Reagan. He will argue that the
government is too big, taxes are too
high, regulations hurt businesses,
welfare programs don't actually fix
poverty, and that society needs more
\quote} traditional values. And after
Ronald Reagan gets elected, pretty
quickly an economic system called
Reaganomics is enacted. This is broken
into three parts. First, you have tax
cuts, meaning that people plus
businesses keep more money. The second
here is deregulation, meaning that there
will be fewer government rules on
industries. [music] And finally, you
have supply-side economics, where
helping businesses grow is supposed to
help everyone, meaning more jobs, more
goods, and a stronger economy overall.
But anyway, I'm sure you are wondering
whether or not this is a good or bad
idea. Well, it's not really my place to
say. Rather, what I will do here is
objectively explain what both political
sides thought of this, and you can
decide whether it's good or bad
yourself. Conservatives would argue that
Reaganomics would grow the economy, make
inflation go down, and allow businesses
to expand. But the liberals, on the
other hand, would argue Reaganomics
basically mostly benefited the rich and
would cause the wealth gap in the US
deficit to grow. And also, something
important to note is that even though
Reagan wanted a smaller government,
programs like Social Security and
Medicare stay, along with an increased
military spending, so the government
really stays a similar size. But before
I end this video, I want to mention that
this rise of conservatism was very
impactful, mostly because the 1980s
wasn't even that long ago. Modern
politics to this day still debate
ideologies from the '80s and beyond. And
also, these conservative '80s weren't
even totally political. You will also
see evangelical Christians rise into
supporting and aligning with the
conservative side. So now it has a clear
social effect. On the screen now are
AP-style questions for this topic. Pause
now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
Only four more to go after this. Let's
keep going.